NAVEEN N RAVI

https://naveen-rn.github.io/ 250 East 6th Street, Apt 0804 \(\infty\) Saint Paul, MN 55101 (832) \(\cdot\) 720 \(\cdot\) 2393 \(\infty\) nravi.research@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Professional Software Engineer with experience in the general areas of parallel and distributed computing. Specifically, my technical skills focuses in design and optimizations in the following areas: (i) distributed parallel programming models and runtime systems for HPC (MPI and OpenSHMEM) and ML (NCCL/RCCL); (ii) parallel computing architectures, and (iii) high-speed network interconnects (HPE Slingshot and Nvidia Infiniband).

EXPERIENCE

Hewlett Packard Enterprise (previously Cray, Inc)

Jan,2016 - present

Senior Systems/Software Engineer

Bloomington, MN

- · HPC and ML communication runtime optimizations for HPE/Cray supercomputers and clusters
- · Tech Lead for Cray programming environment software stacks including Cray MPI and Cray SHMEM
- · Participate and represent HPE/Cray in OpenSHMEM and MPI standards committee

Cray, Inc
May,2015 - Dec,2015
Intern
Saint Paul, MN

- · Research and prototype new communication protocols in Cray SHMEM library
- · Optimize Global Arrays library for NAMD and NWChem Chemistry applications

University of Houston

Sep,2013 - May,2015

Research Assistant - HPC Tools

Houston, TX

- · Research Assistant to Prof. Barbara Chapman
- · Explore strategies for communication runtime optimizations for scalable parallel systems

EDUCATION

University of Minnesota, Twin Cities

Aug, 2022 - Present

Ph.D. in Computer Science

University of Houston, Main Campus

Aug, 2013 - Dec, 2015

M.S. in Computer Science - Specialization in Parallel & Distributed Systems

Anna University, India

Sep,2007 - May,2011

Bachelors in Engineering - Electrical & Electronics Engineering

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Programming Languages

Parallel Programming Models & Libraries

Network Libraries

Architectures

System Architectures Network Architectures

Device Architectures

C/C++, Python

OpenSHMEM, MPI, NCCL/RCCL

Libfabric, UCX, Verbs

HPE Cray Supercomputers & Clusters

Aarch64 (Nvidia Grace), x86_64 (AMD Milan) HPE Slingshot, Cray Aries, Nvidia Infiniband

AMD (MI250X, MI300A), Nvidia (A100, H100)

STANDARDIZATION ACTIVITIES

- 1. **OpenSHMEM standardization Effort**, Participate and represent HPE in OpenSHMEM standards committee. http://openshmem.org/.
- 2. **MPI Forum**, Participate and represent HPE in the standardization forum for the Message Passing Interface (MPI). https://www.mpi-forum.org/.

AWARDS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- 1. **Best Paper Award**, 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Model(PGAS 2014).
- 2. Graduate Assistant Tution Fellowship, September 2013 May 2015.
- 3. **Best Undergraduate Student Project**, Mepco Schlenk Eng. College, Anna University, India, 2011.

FUNDED PROJECTS

- 1. Intra-node MPI Support for Intel GPUs. Contract in relation to the Collaboration of Intel and HPE (Cray) for Argonne Aurora Supercomputer, 2021.
- 2. Multi-NIC and Multi-GPU Network Support for MPI. Collaboration of Oak Ridge, Argonne, and Livermore (CORAL-2) Contract, 2022.
- 3. GPU Triggered Communication for MPI Point-to-Point Communication. Collaboration of Oak Ridge, Argonne, and Livermore (CORAL-2) Contract, 2022.
- 4. GPU Triggered Communication for MPI One-sided Communication. Collaboration of Oak Ridge, Argonne, and Livermore (CORAL-2) Contract, 2023.
- 5. OpenSHMEM Append communication scheme for sorting. Numerically Challenged, a pathfinding project for next-gen HPE Slingshot NIC, 2024.

PUBLICATIONS

My full name is **Naveen Namashivayam Ravichandrasekaran** and I author all conference and workshop publications as **Naveen Namashivayam**.

Refereed Conference and Workshop Publications

- 1. T.Groves, **N.Namashivayam**, B.Cook, B.Friesen, N.Keen, D.Trebotich, N.J.Wright, B.Alverson, D.Roweth, and K.Underwood. "Not All Applications Have Boring Communication Patterns: Profiling Message Matching with BMM". In Proceedings of Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience.
- 2. **N.Namashivayam**, S.Mehta, and P.C.Yew. "Variable-sized Blocks for Locality-aware SpMV". In Proceedings of International Symposium on Code Generation and Optimization (CGO 2021).
- 3. **N.Namashivayam**, B.Long, D.Eachempati, B.Cernohous, and M.Pagel. "A Modern Fortran Interface in OpenSHMEM.". In Proceedings of ACM Transactions on Parallel Computing, August, 2020.
- 4. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, D.Pou, and M.Pagel. "Introducing Cray OpenSHMEMX A Modular Multi-Communication Layer OpenSHMEM Implementation.". In Proceedings of Fifth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies, August, 2018, Hanover, USA.

- 5. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, K.Kandalla, D.Pou, J.Robichaux, J.Dinan, and M.Pagel. "Symmetric Memory Partitions in OpenSHMEM: A case study with Intel KNL". In Proceedings of Fourth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Big Compute and Big Data Convergence, August, 2017, Annapolis, USA.
- 6. K.Kandalla, P.Mendygral, N.Radcliffe, B.Cernohous, **N.Namashivayam**, K.McMahon, C.Sadlo and M.Pagel "Current State of the Cray MPT Software Stacks on the Cray XC Series Supercomputers". In proceedings of Cray User Group Meeting, 2017, Redmond, USA.
- 7. N.Namashivayam, D.Knaak, B.Cernohous, N.Radcliffe, and M.Pagel. "An Evaluation of Thread-Safe and Contexts-Domains Features in Cray SHMEM". In Proceedings of Third Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Enhancing OpenSHMEM for Hybrid Environments, August, 2016, Hanover, USA.
- 8. N.Namashivayam, D.Eachempati, D.Khaldi and B.Chapman. "OpenSHMEM as a Portable Communication Layer for PGAS Models A Case Study with Coarray Fortran". In Proceedings of IEEE Cluster 2015, September, 2015, Chicago, USA.
- 9. N.Namashivayam, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati and B.Chapman. "Extending the Strided Communication Interface in OpenSHMEM". In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, USA.
- 10. D.Knaak, and **N.Namashivayam**. "Proposing OpenSHMEM Extensions Towards a Future for Hybrid Programming and Heterogeneous Computing", In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, USA.
- 11. **N.Namashivayam**, S.Ghosh, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati, and B.Chapman. "Native Mode-Based Optimizations of Remote Memory Accesses in OpenSHMEM for Intel Xeon Phi", 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Models (PGAS 2014).

Thesis

• N.Namashivayam. "OpenSHMEM as an Effective Communication Layer for PGAS Models". Master's Thesis, University of Houston, October, 2015.

Other Publications

- 1. **N.Namashivayam**, K. Kandalla, T. White, L.Kaplan, and M. Pagel. "Exploring Fully Offloaded GPU Stream-Aware Message Passing". arXiv preprint arXiv:2306.15773.
- 2. **N.Namashivayam**, K. Kandalla, T. White, N. Radcliffle, L.Kaplan, and M. Pagel. "Exploring GPU Stream-Aware Message Passing using Triggered Operations". arXiv preprint arXiv:2306.15773.

PEER REVIEW PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- 1. Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies 2016, 2017, 2018, and 2021.
- 2. IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (TPDS).

PATENTS

- 1. Offloading network communication operation synchronizations to accelerator streams, 2022.
- 2. Efficient inter-process broadcast in a distributed system, 2023.
- 3. Adaptive triggered operation management in a network interface controller, 2023.